<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<plan>
  <metadata>
    <title>4th Pass Debug Factorial — GCP SkyPilot with SWAG + Calibration</title>
    <branch>test/debug-factorial-4th-pass</branch>
    <date>2026-03-21</date>
    <status>designing</status>
    <priority>P0 — validates full factorial on cloud GPU before production spend</priority>
    <skill>factorial-monitor</skill>
    <estimated-cost>~$6-10 GCP L4 spot (24 trainable + 2 zero-shot, 2 epochs)</estimated-cost>
    <report-output>docs/planning/run-debug-factorial-experiment-report-4th-pass.md</report-output>
  </metadata>

  <user-prompt-verbatim>
    <!-- User's original prompt saved verbatim as requested -->
    I think any further training after 2 epochs for 5 more epochs would improve the
    results so would not make too much of the numbers, update the report accordingly
    and commit and push, and then we can next create a 4th pass plan then finally for
    the Debug run on Skypilot+GCP as we did in
    /home/petteri/Dropbox/github-personal/minivess-mlops/docs/planning/run-debug-factorial-experiment.xml
    and now create the xml plan to
    /home/petteri/Dropbox/github-personal/minivess-mlops/docs/planning/run-debug-factorial-experiment-4th-pass.xml
    and then plan how to run this /factorial-monitor Skill, and the .sh should actually
    stay more or less the same? Obviously now SWAG is used before the old erroneously
    named SWA that was used as name for checkpoint averaging. Ask A LOT OF QUESTIONS in
    the interactive format when designing this plan so that we are 100% that we are
    aligned before burning the GCP credits for this debug factorial! As in the full
    factorial design, but only for 2 epochs (both training and SWAG), one fold and with
    half of the subjects. Otherwise the run should be EXACTLY as the real
    "publication-gate run" that we still have not completed. And that would obviously
    come after this run if we have everything running ok! Remember that in the last
    Skypilot+GCP run
    (/home/petteri/Dropbox/github-personal/minivess-mlops/docs/planning/run-debug-factorial-experiment-report.md),
    only Dynunet actually worked and we have no idea if SAM3, vesselfm and the mamba
    network will work! So put extra work when planning this .XML so that we can get the
    models running, and now we have the specific test suite also developed that should be
    run on the machine that it responsible for all the heavy GPU tasks (L4 now) which we
    should test once before running all the cells of the factorial design, and make sure
    that it characterizes the instance, and then checks that all the models actually
    train? We should have test suite at least implemented to catch all those issues
    before
    /home/petteri/Dropbox/github-personal/minivess-mlops/docs/planning/run-debug-factorial-experiment-report.md
    without actually start running the real experiments. Should we even design a new
    Prefect Flow for this? Flow that basically has sub-flows: 1) something that can
    monitor the new configs where L4.yaml is now and if we add there a new .yaml, this
    Prefect Flow is then triggered, 2) one sub-flow that would always run once without
    much hard-coding, and it should adaptively as well figure from the .yaml used to
    trigger Train Flow which models are being tested and which model tests should run!
    E.g. if we run a factorial design with SAM3 and dynunet, no need to run the tests
    for vesselfm or mamba this time. If you think that this new Prefect Flow design and
    implementation is too massive, we can defer it? But either way create a P1 issue on
    this Prefect Flow for Instance testing. Open a PR for current branch and automerge
    it first after running the full prod suite first with no errors found, and then let's
    designing these new tasks to test/debug-factorial-4th-pass!
  </user-prompt-verbatim>

  <design-questions>
    <!-- These questions MUST be answered before the plan is finalized -->
    <!-- Status: PENDING — awaiting user answers -->

    <question id="Q1" topic="SWAG in factorial design">
      The 1st pass used "SWA" (which was actually checkpoint averaging). Now we have
      real SWAG (Maddox 2019). In the 4th pass factorial:

      (a) Should SWAG be a POST-TRAINING plugin that runs after each training job
          completes (i.e., train 2 epochs → then SWAG 2 more epochs on same GPU)?
      (b) Or should SWAG be a separate SkyPilot job that runs AFTER all training
          jobs complete (like the post-training flow in the 1st pass plan)?

      Option (a) means each job takes ~2× longer but no separate orchestration.
      Option (b) keeps training jobs fast but adds a second wave of SkyPilot jobs.

      My recommendation: (a) — integrate SWAG into the training job. The SWAG plugin
      resumes training on the same checkpoint, same GPU, same data. Launching a separate
      job wastes setup time (Docker pull, DVC pull, model load).
    </question>

    <question id="Q2" topic="Post-training factor">
      The factorial design currently has: model × loss × aux_calib.
      With SWAG, we add a post_training factor: {none, swag, checkpoint_averaging}.

      Should the 4th pass factorial be:
        4 models × 3 losses × 2 aux_calib × 3 post_training = 72 conditions (+ 2 zero-shot)?
      Or keep it at:
        4 models × 3 losses × 2 aux_calib × 2 post_training = 48 conditions (+ 2 zero-shot)?
        (dropping checkpoint_averaging since 2nd pass showed it's negligible)
      Or even simpler for debug:
        4 models × 3 losses × 2 aux_calib = 24 training jobs, then apply SWAG to ALL?
        (SWAG applied post-hoc to every checkpoint, no extra training jobs)

      My recommendation: 24 training jobs + SWAG applied post-hoc to all. This matches
      the 1st pass design (same number of training jobs) but replaces checkpoint averaging
      with SWAG. Keeps debug cost at ~$6-10.
    </question>

    <question id="Q3" topic="Instance validation flow">
      You mentioned a Prefect Flow for instance testing. The idea is:
      1. When a new GPU instance starts, run model-specific tests BEFORE training
      2. Adaptively select which tests to run based on the factorial design

      This would have caught Glitches #9 (LoRA Conv2d), #10 (mamba-ssm), and #12
      (zero-shot max_epochs=0) from the 1st pass before burning GPU time.

      Design options:
      (a) Full Prefect sub-flow with config-file monitoring — ambitious, reusable
      (b) Simple Python script that runs in SkyPilot setup phase — pragmatic, fast
      (c) Deferred to P1 issue — just run existing tests/gpu_instance/ manually first

      Given this is blocking the 4th pass, I recommend (b) for now + (a) as P1 issue.
      A simple script in the SkyPilot YAML setup phase that:
      - Detects which models are in the factorial design (from env vars)
      - Runs model-specific smoke tests (import, build, 1-batch forward pass)
      - Fails fast if any model can't even load

      This catches 90% of issues without a full Prefect flow.
    </question>

    <question id="Q4" topic="Known blockers from 1st pass">
      The 1st pass had these unresolved model failures:

      | Model | Glitch | Status | What needs fixing |
      |-------|--------|--------|-------------------|
      | sam3_topolora | #9: LoRA on Conv2d | OPEN | LoRA targeting must skip Conv2d |
      | mambavesselnet | #10: mamba-ssm not compiled | OPEN | Docker image needs INSTALL_MAMBA=1 |
      | sam3_vanilla (zero-shot) | #12: max_epochs=0 | OPEN | Pydantic ge=1 constraint |
      | vesselfm (zero-shot) | #12: max_epochs=0 | OPEN | Same Pydantic constraint |

      Should we:
      (a) Fix ALL four before the 4th pass (adds 1-2 days of work)
      (b) Fix sam3_topolora + zero-shot (likely quick), defer mamba-ssm (Docker rebuild)
      (c) Run 4th pass with only dynunet + sam3_hybrid (known working), defer rest

      My recommendation: (b) — fix LoRA targeting and zero-shot validation, but defer
      mamba-ssm Docker compilation to a separate issue. That gives us 3/4 models working
      (dynunet, sam3_hybrid, sam3_topolora) + 2 zero-shot baselines.
    </question>

    <question id="Q5" topic="Checkpoint persistence (P0 from 1st pass)">
      Glitch #8 from the 1st pass: ALL 11 succeeded training jobs had LOST checkpoints
      because MLflow Cloud Run was configured with --serve-artifacts (proxying), which
      doesn't persist to GCS.

      Is this fixed? The fix was:
      - MLflow Cloud Run with --no-serve-artifacts
      - Direct GCS artifact storage (gs://minivess-mlops-mlflow-artifacts)
      - Or: SkyPilot file_mounts to sync checkpoints to GCS directly

      If NOT fixed, this is still a P0 blocker for the 4th pass.
    </question>

    <question id="Q6" topic="Docker base image rebuild">
      The 4th pass needs a Docker image with:
      - All SWAG plugin code (from this branch)
      - All calibration metrics code
      - Fixed LoRA targeting (if Q4 answer includes sam3_topolora)
      - Optionally: mamba-ssm compiled (if Q4 answer includes mambavesselnet)

      This means we need to:
      1. Merge this branch to main
      2. Rebuild Docker base image from main
      3. Push to GAR

      Should we do this as part of the 4th pass prep, or is there a faster path?
    </question>

    <question id="Q7" topic="Calibration metrics in factorial YAML">
      The debug_factorial.yaml doesn't currently reference calibration metrics.
      Should we add calibration_metrics config to the factorial YAML, or are they
      automatically computed by the training loop (SegmentationMetrics) and
      analysis flow (UnifiedEvaluationRunner)?

      From the 3rd pass: Tier 1 calibration metrics (ECE, Brier, NLL) are computed
      in the training validation loop. Tier 2 (ACE, BA-ECE) are computed in the
      analysis flow. No YAML changes needed for metrics.

      But: should the BiostatisticsConfig be updated to include calibration metrics
      as ANOVA response variables for the 4th pass?
    </question>

    <question id="Q8" topic="run_factorial.sh changes">
      The .sh script should "stay more or less the same" as you said. The only
      changes I see needed are:

      (a) Add SWAG_EPOCHS env var to SkyPilot launch (if SWAG runs in-job per Q1)
      (b) Add SWAG_LR, SWAG_MAX_RANK env vars
      (c) Update job naming: include "swag" in condition name if applicable

      Or should the .sh stay IDENTICAL and SWAG be handled entirely by the
      post-training flow (downstream, not in training jobs)?
    </question>
  </design-questions>

  <!-- Phases will be filled in after design questions are answered -->
  <phases>
    <phase id="0" name="Pre-Flight: Fix Known Blockers">
      <description>PLACEHOLDER — depends on Q4 answers</description>
    </phase>
    <phase id="1" name="Instance Validation (GPU Smoke Tests)">
      <description>PLACEHOLDER — depends on Q3 answers</description>
    </phase>
    <phase id="2" name="Launch Training Conditions">
      <description>PLACEHOLDER — depends on Q1, Q2, Q8 answers</description>
    </phase>
    <phase id="3" name="Post-Training (SWAG)">
      <description>PLACEHOLDER — depends on Q1, Q2 answers</description>
    </phase>
    <phase id="4" name="Analysis Flow with Calibration Metrics">
      <description>PLACEHOLDER — depends on Q7 answers</description>
    </phase>
    <phase id="5" name="Biostatistics Flow">
      <description>PLACEHOLDER — depends on Q7 answers</description>
    </phase>
    <phase id="6" name="Report">
      <description>Write 4th pass report</description>
    </phase>
  </phases>

  <cross-reference>
    <report file="docs/planning/run-debug-factorial-experiment-report.md" relation="1st-pass-glitches"/>
    <report file="docs/planning/run-debug-factorial-experiment-report-2nd-pass-local.md" relation="2nd-pass-local"/>
    <report file="docs/planning/run-debug-factorial-experiment-report-3rd-pass-local.md" relation="3rd-pass-local"/>
    <plan file="docs/planning/run-debug-factorial-experiment.xml" relation="1st-pass-plan"/>
    <plan file="docs/planning/run-debug-factorial-experiment-report-3rd-pass-plan.xml" relation="3rd-pass-plan"/>
    <script file="scripts/run_factorial.sh" relation="primary-executable"/>
    <skypilot file="deployment/skypilot/train_factorial.yaml" relation="per-condition-task"/>
    <config file="configs/experiment/debug_factorial.yaml" relation="debug-config"/>
  </cross-reference>
</plan>
